Okay בוקר טוב, boker tov, today's דף daf is פ''א, Pa-Aleph, and
we pick up with the משנה Mishnah on פ' ע''ב. Pey Amud
Beis. And we're still dealing with various amounts of sizes of objects
for carrying. So אדמה, Adamah, ground, earth, probably used in some type
of, clearly used in some type of a mold or something. Clay,
right, thank you, better.
כחותם המרצופים, Kechosem hamartzufim, like the, like a seal used for, like,
tzamati sounds like it's described like on chests, you know, on some
type of boxes that you put a seal on it to make
sure that it hasn't been opened. דברי רבי עקיבא, Divrei Rabbi Akiva,
that's what Rabbi Akiva says. וחכמים אומרים כחותם האיגרות. Vachachamim omrim kechosem
ha'igaros.
No, like a seal put on letters, so obviously that would be
smaller. האיגרות Ha'igaros are letters?
Leather or did you say letters?
Letters, okay. זבל וחול הדק,
Zevel
vechol
hadak,
so we've seen this quoted before, manure and fine sand, which was
used somehow as a type of manure, of a type of a
fertilizer. כדי לזבל קלח של כרוב, Kedei lezavel klach shel k'ruv, in
order to fertilize a one stalk, thank you, of cabbage. דברי רבי
עקיבא. Divrei Rabbi Akiva. That's what Rabbi Akiva says. וחכמים אומרים כדי
לזבל כרישא, Vachachamim omrim kedei lezavel k'reisha, in order to fertilize a
leek. All right, so... Yes,
חול הגס, Chol hagass, coarse sand, thick sand, כדי ליתן על מלא
כף סיד, kedei litein al melo kaf sid, קנה, kaneh, in order,
a מלא כף סיד, melo kaf sid, in order to put on
a like on the top of a of a trowel. If you
look at רש''י, Rashi,
second wide line, בגמרא פירש כף של סיידין, bigmara pireish kaf shel
sayadin, a
like a spoon or whatever, applicator for that they used by those
that plaster, trowel בלע''ז, be-la'az, so there you go, on a trowel.
Okay, so they would add some thick sand when they were applying
plaster, we'll find out about that. So the amount that would go
on one head of a trowel.
So, where were we?
Okay. קנה, Kaneh, now a reed, כדי לעשות קולמוס, kedei la'asos kulmus,
in order to make out of it a quill. ואם היה עבה,
Ve'im haya avei, if it was thick, so you couldn't use it
for a quill, או מרוסס, o merusas, or if it was like
split, cracked, so you couldn't use it for a quill, כדי לבשל
בו ביצה קלה שבביצים, kedei levashel bo beitzah kallah shebeveitzim,
in order to cook using it as firewood to cook a very
easy egg. We'll see what easy means, a light egg, an egg
that can cook easily, that and that amount to use as for
the firewood, well we'll see about that, that amount to use for
firewood to create a fire that would allow you to cook an
egg. טרופה ונתונה באילפס, Trufah u-nesunah be-ilpas, if it was like scrambled,
you know, beaten, and put into a pan. So, in order to
make a scrambled egg. All right, so let's take a look. So
גמרא Gemara says, מלא כף סיד, melo kaf sid, תנא כדי ליתן
על פי כף של סיידין. tana kedei litein al pi kaf shel
sayadin. So what does that mean, the full of the spoon of
the plasterer? It's not clear what that means. So the ברייתא Beraita
explains a little better, it means to put on the opening of
this applicator of plaster. Okay,
מאן תנא דחול מעלי ליה לסיד, man tana dechol ma'ali lei lesid,
who is the תנא Tanna that says that sand is good, helpful
for plastering? Because obviously why would we measure it based on the
amount you put on an applicator of plaster unless it was something
that you would use in plastering? סו אמר רב חסדא רבי יהודה
היא, So amar Rav Chisda Rabbi Yehuda hi, it's רבי יהודה. Rabbi
Yehuda. דתניא, Detanya, תנא ברייתא, tana Beraita, לא יסוד אדם את ביתו
בסיד אלא אם כן עירב בו תבן או חול, lo yasud adam
es beiso be-sid ella im kein irav bo teven o chol,
that a person should not plaster his house with plaster because these
are one of the things that is taught at the end of
סוטה Sotah in the תוספתא סוטה Tosefta Sotah that we don't do
after the חורבן Churban because it's, you know, for אבילות aveilus for
ירושלים, Yerushalayim, so you don't have everything that looks beautiful and perfect.
So don't plaster your house with plaster unless you've mixed into it
some straw or some sand and then it's not like, you know,
perfect pristine plaster. רבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda omer, תבן מותר, teven
mutar, I agree with straw that's okay as a way of addressing
this חורבן Churban aspect, חול אסור, chol assur, but sand no. Why?
מפני שהוא טרק סיד, mipnei shehu trach sid, so it strengthens the
plaster, it's clearly the word סיד sid there, anyway somehow it's a
strengthening of the plaster, it makes it better, not worse. So if
the idea is to do something as a זכר לחורבן, zecher le-churban,
that's not זכר לחורבן, zecher le-churban, that makes it better. So you
see that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda feels that you would add sand
to plaster. So our משנה Mishnah that says you measure sand by
the amount that was added to plaster and that's something that you
would try to do, that's רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. But the חכמים
Chachamim who feel that that's actually done as a זכר לחורבן, zecher
le-churban, presumably they feel that normally sand would not be added to
plaster, it's not good for plastering.
I should ask the builders.
All right, so let's see. So גמרא Gemara says, what can it
say? רבא אמר אפילו תימא רבנן, Rava amar afilu teima rabanan, even
the rabbis would agree that sand is something that is added to
plaster that makes it better. קלקולו זהו תיקונו. kilkulo zehu tikuno. It
is,
it's making it bad is what makes it good. Now what does
that mean? So רש"י Rashi says there's interesting ways of reading this,
but the way רש"י Rashi says what it means is that because
it makes the plaster worst, worse, that's why we allow you to
use it. So once we have now told you that you can,
that you need to add the sand because of זכר לחורבן, zecher
l'churban, now having the sand allows you to use the plaster, right?
If you didn't have the sand, you couldn't use the plaster because
it'd be a problem, it wouldn't be appropriate, it wouldn't be, you
know, it would be too nice. So because the sand makes it
worse, that makes it allowed to be used. And now with the
given the rabbinic restrictions, sand is something you want to add to
plaster because it lets you use the plaster because it makes it
זכר לחורבן. zecher l'churban. Okay, so therefore that's why actually even for
the רבנן, Rabbanan, you would, you would, you know, you would determine
it based on the sand since this is now a necessary ingredient
to the plaster. That's by the way an interesting phrase קלקולו זהו
תיקונו. kilkulo zehu tikuno. It gets used in other contexts, you know,
by sort of saying that because something, you know, became worse, it
got better. Like there's a famous תשובה teshuva from,
from, what's his name?
From the בנין ציון, Binyan Tzion,
from רב עטלינגר Rav Ettlinger on the, who deals with like the
whole issue about, you know, מחלל שבת mechallel Shabbat nowadays
after the השכלה Haskalah and so on when, you know, most of
כל ישראל Klal Yisrael is no longer שומר שבת. shomer Shabbat. So
do they have the status, is do we apply the same principles
of מחלל שבת? mechallel Shabbat? So he says some, he says, he
uses the phrase קלקולו זהו תיקונו kilkulo zehu tikuno that basically because
everybody has, is now מחלל שבת, mechallel Shabbat, not everybody, you know,
the vast majority of the Jewish people, so it no longer has
the same type of a, you know, sort of status or stigma
in the sense that exclusionary, you know, basis for exclusion. So sometimes,
you know, it's an interesting phrase which is because what makes it
worse is now what actually made it better. So okay. So anyway,
therefore even the רבנן Rabbanan would agree that you measure it based
on the, on the, on the sand because that's what you would
put, have to put in nowadays in order to allow you to
use the plaster. All right, so now the גמרא Gemara continues, קנה
כדי לעשות קולמוס, kaneh kidei la'asot kulmus,
a reed in order to make a quill. תנא קולמוס המגיע לקשרי
אצבעותיו. tana kulmus hamagi'a le'kishrei etzbe'otav. You know, it's like if you
think of like a little, like a little stub of a pencil,
how big of a quill? So the quill just big enough to
get to like, you know, the, the knuckles of your finger. So
which knuckles? So the גמרא Gemara says, meaning minimum size of a
quill to write, right? So בעי רב אשי קשר עליון או קשר
תחתון, ba'ei Rav Ashi kesher elyon o kesher tachton, the upper or
the bottom knuckle? Which רש"י Rashi says the upper one means the
knuckle that combines the finger to the hand or the bottom one
which is presumably, you know, the,
this knuckle, the knuckle here in the middle of your, of your
finger. I mean you actually have two knuckles here in your finger,
but okay. Anyway, so the גמרא Gemara says, which one is that?
תיקו teiku and we let, we don't know, we let that question
stand. Okay.
So now, that's about the quill. ואם היה עבה, ve'im hayah aveh,
if it was thick or, or split, then it would be to
make a, enough to make a small fire in order to cook
to fry an egg. So תנא טרופה בשמן, tana trufah b'shemen, so
you're frying the egg, which makes it, which means that you need
less of a fire, it goes quicker. So it's mixed with oil
ונתונה באילפס u'netunah b'ilpas and put in the frying pan. אמר ליה
מר בריה דרבינא לבריה, amar leih Mar breih d'Ravina l'abreih, so מר
Mar the son of רבינא Ravina said to his son, נישמיע לך
ביצת קלה מאי? nishmi'a lach beitzah kalah mai? What are, what does
this mean, a light egg? It says a light egg. So now
we've decided that it was frying it and you it's scrambled, but
what does this mean, a light egg? אמר ליה ביעתא דצילצלא. amar
leih beita d'tziltzala. It's an egg of a צילצלא, tziltzala, which is
some type of a bird which presumably is very small. I don't
know, how do they translate צילצלא tziltzala over there?
I don't know. Turtle dove. Turtle dove?
That's what?
What, yeah, well that's, turtle dove is used, יונה. yonah. Anyway, מאי
טעמא משום דזוטרא? mai ta'ama mishum d'zutra? Why are you saying that?
Because it's small, so maybe therefore it requires less firewood. אימא דצפירתא?
eima d'tzipirta? How about a צפירתא tzipirta which is even smaller? I
don't know what they say. Hummingbird. Hummingbird? Okay. סנונית. snunit. Sparrow. Sparrow?
Is sparrow kosher?
Sparrow's kosher?
Sparrow's kosher, I don't know. Why not? It's צילצלא, tziltzala, it's a...
what? There you go, now we know. Okay, אישתיק, ishtik, so he
was silent. אמר ליה מידי שמיע לך בהא? amar leih midi shmi'a
lach be'ha? So he said back to his father, so נו, nu,
have you heard anything about this, about what קלה kalah means? I
was just trying to pick a small bird, but you know, so
what have you heard it means? אמר ליה הכי אמר רב ששת
ביצת תרנגולת.
amar leih hachi amar Rav Sheshet
beitzat tarnegolet. Ah, normal, yeah, a normal egg of, of a hen,
of a chicken. ומאי קרי לה ביצת קלה? u'mai kari lah beitzah
kalah? So why do they call it a light egg?
משום דקדים ומבשלא יתיר מכל ביצת תרנגולת. mishum d'kadim u'mevashla yatir mikol
beitzat tarnegolet. We're not talking about quantity, we're talking about how easily
it cooks, and no egg cooks easier, quicker than a chicken egg.
Normally when we're dealing with food we go by a גרוגרת, grogeret,
a pressed date. Now we're dealing with the size of an egg,
which is larger. So it's true we're talking about firewood, but it's
the firewood needed to cook an amount of food. And the amount
of food of significance usually is the size of a date. So
how come we're dealing with here the food the size of an
egg? אמר ליה הכי אמר רב נחמן. amar leh hachi amar rav
nachman. Ah, good point. Here's what רב נחמן rav nachman says. כגרוגרת
מביצה קלה. ke-grogeret mi-beitzah kalah. We don't mean to cook a whole
egg. We mean to cook a גרוגרת-sized grogeret worth of an egg.
So it's the amount of firewood needed to cook a גרוגרת-sized grogeret
worth of a chicken's egg, scrambled with oil. Okay, and that's the
amount of reeds that you would need that is minimum of significance
if you cannot make a quill out of it. Okay.
So now we move on to the next משנה. mishnah. So we're
going one thing after another. So we've done with various reeds and
sand and whatever. עצם. etzem. How about bones? כדי לעשות תרבד kedei
la'asot tarvad in order to make some type of a spoon out
of.
And these spoons could come in various sizes, but this would be
a small size for one. רבי יהודה אומר כדי לעשות ממנו כף
rabbi yehuda omer kedei la'asot mimenu kaf in order to make out
of it a כף. kaf. Let's see what that is in a
minute. It's basically teeth for a lock. זכוכית, zechuchit, glass, כדי לגרור
בו ראשי הקרכר kedei ligror bo rashei ha-karkar in order to use
to scrape the head
of a קרכר karkar which is a thing used in the, it
was like a stick used in the weaving process. We'll find out
more about that when we get to weaving.
צרור או אבן, tzror o even, a rock or a stone, not
sure exactly the difference, one is maybe a chip of a rock,
I don't know, כדי לזרוק בעוף kedei lizrok be-of in order that
you would use to throw it at a bird in order to
scare away like birds, you know, let's say that were coming to
eat on your, eat at your crops. רבי אליעזר בר יעקב אומר
כדי לזרוק בבהמה. rabbi eliezer bar yaakov omer kedei lizrok bi-vehemah. No,
you need a bigger one in order to throw at an animal,
like whether your cows were moving, were going in the wrong direction
or something, or some animal's coming to attack your animals. Okay, so
those are the various sizes of the stones. So let's see what
the גמרא gemara says. למימרא דשיעורא דרבי יהודה נפיש? lemeimra de-shiura de-rabbi
yehudah nafish? Once again going to this, that since in one משנה
mishnah רבי יהודה rabbi yehudah had a smaller size than the rabbis,
it's more מחמיר machmir by the rabbis. The גמרא gemara consistently assumes
that he's always more מחמיר machmir when it comes to sizes of
carrying on שבת. shabbat. It's so strange again that the גמרא gemara
assumes that it's a general approach of I'm going to be a
מחמיר, machmir, I'm going to be a מקיל, meikel, rather than a
question about like just each case on its own merit. Anyway, so
here when רבי יהודה rabbi yehudah says in order to make the
teeth for a lock, the גמרא gemara assumes that that's a larger
amount than the size of a spoon. So therefore how could that
be? How could רבי יהודה's rabbi yehudah be a larger amount and
therefore effectively be more מקיל? meikel? הא קיימא לן דשיעורא דרבנן נפיש?
ha kayma lan de-shiura de-rabbanan nafish?
Don't we, don't we know that the size of the rabbis is
larger and he is usually the one that's more מחמיר? machmir? He
is usually the one that's more strict. אמר עולא חפי פותחת. amar
ulla chappei potachat. So it is again it is the... so what
רשי rashi says the switch was, I actually jumped a little to
the end, was that initially it thought it meant the entire lock,
that the entire lock was out of bone. And then the and
that would be much larger than the amount for a spoon. And
then the answer is no, no, no, not the entire lock, just
to make the teeth for the lock. Okay, you know the inner
mechanism in which the key would go, so it's the inner mechanism
which he's talking about and that's smaller than the spoon. Okay, so
תנו רבנן. tanu rabbanan. So now we're going to say something about
the teeth for the lock.
חפי פותחת, chappei potachat, teeth for the lock, טהורים. tehorim. They're טהור
tahor because they're not yet usable in the state that they are
in.
קבען בפותחת. keva'an be-potachat. If you put them inside the lock, into
the inner mechanism, טמאים. tme'im. They're טמא. tamei. Now רשי rashi says
we're still talking about bone, those made out of bone. תוספות tosafot
based on a lot of evidence says we know we're talking about
metal. Bone is not טמא tamei if it's not like wood, doesn't
have a בית קיבול, beit kibul, doesn't have a receptacle. And here
these teeth don't really have a receptacle, so therefore we're talking about
metal, that it's a metal mechanism. So metal, as you know, a
metal vessel is טמא tamei even without a receptacle. So therefore when
they're just by themselves they're not yet usable, but if they've been
put into the lock, then the lock is defined by the inner
mechanism, and since that is metal, therefore it is טמא. tamei. It
can become טמא. tamei. It is susceptible for טומאה. tumah. ושל גל,
u-shel gal, if they however are the mechanism of a lock inside
of a door, אף על פי שחיברן בדלת וקבען במסמרים, af al
pi she-chibaran be-delet u-keva'an be-masmerim, even though you put them in the
door and actually like really connected them with nails, טהורים. tehorim. They're
still טהור tahor שכל המחובר לקרקע הרי הוא כקרקע she-kol ha-mechubar le-karka
harei hu ke-karka because by themselves they're not usable and in the
door they're part of something that is attached to the ground. It's
part of a house, it's part of a building, and therefore things
that are attached to the ground cannot become טמא. tamei.
Okay, so not something like those master locks that
you put in like you know... no, no, we're talking about like
a mechanism inside of your door like you have... okay. Okay. So
זכוכית כדי לגרור, zechuchit kedei ligror,
glass in order to use to scrape the top of this
קרכר. karkar. of
a wood thing that was used for beating the wool in the
loom, so תנא סכוכית tana sechuchit for some people it says סכוכית
sechuchit I mean whatever it's spelled sometimes סכוכית sechuchit not זכוכית zechuchit
כדי לפצוא בה שני מימין כאחת kedei liftzoa bah shenei mimin ke-achat
in order to like you know to again to like you know
separate these two strings as one that are let's say intertwined again
on the loom so used in this way of straightening out the
threads of a weave. Okay. צרור או אבן כדי לזרוק בעוף ר'
אליעזר אומר שניהם tzror o even kedei lizrok be-of Rebbi Eliezer omer
sheneihem a rock or stone to throw at a bird or to
throw at an animal. So why this difference? אמר ר' יעקב אמר
ר' יוחנן Amar Rebbi Yaakov amar Rebbi Yochanan
I can't read this word. What is that? והוא? vehu? What? והוא,
vehu, I'm sorry, it's just scraped out of my גמרא. Gemara. והוא
שמרגשת בה. vehu shemargashet bah. It's only where the animal can feel
it, meaning you throw it at the animal
but if the animal isn't affected by it, it's not big enough
to bother the animal, obviously it doesn't make a difference.
Now are you talking about the עוף of or the בהמה? beheima?
Well, presumably the בהמה. beheima. Now רש"י Rashi says what? What?
So why, anyway, רש"י Rashi says what's the difference? רש"י Rashi or
תוספות Tosafot says what's the difference between עוף of and בהמה beheima
because you know you could just yell at the bird and scare
it away. So the other one said, yeah, even though you might
throw a rock at a bird, you normally you want you save
the rocks for throwing at the at the cats at the animals.
The birds you can just scare them away otherwise. Okay so it
has to be אבן even that you throw at the animal and
the animal actually cares about it and moves away. וכמה שיעורו? ve-khama
shiuro? And how big is it? תניא ר' אליעזר בן יעקב אומר
Tanya Rebbi Eliezer ben Yaakov omer משקל עשרה זוז. mishkal asara zuz.
It has to weigh the same as עשרה זוז, asara zuz, whatever
that is. Quite funny, you know, it says right, that's like a
standard joke that you know
somebody goes into somebody's house in מאה שערים Meah Shearim and sees
like these small rocks and says set them aside so that they're
not מוקצה muktzah so he can throw rocks at the cars on
שבת Shabbos and then he goes to somebody else's house he sees
rocks much bigger. He says well why are these so much bigger
than your neighbor's house? This is שיעור
חזון איש.
shiur
Chazon Ish.
So anyway, so here's exactly the size of the stone to throw
at the
cows, right? So it's got to be it's got to be it's
got to be weighs עשרה זוז asara zuz and that's the significance
for carrying a rock. Okay, so זונים Zonim came to the בית
המדרש. beis hamidrash. זונים Zonim which is we know a story about
בייתוס בן זונים. Beisus ben Zonim. Anyway here is זונים Zonim himself
comes to the בית המדרש. beis hamidrash. אמר להו Amar lehu and
he said to them, רבותי, rabosai, my masters, אבנים של בית הכסא
שיעורן בכמה? avanim shel beis hakisei shiuran be-khama? How about stones that
are used for the bathroom? How big are they? Now presumably either
that you're חייב chayav if you carry them, because they would use
stones basically as toilet paper to wipe themselves. So that's a use.
So maybe a standard stone hasn't been designated as such, you would
say the standard use is to throw at animals but maybe if
it's set aside there it also would have to be a particular
shape to be functional to use that way, but if it is
that shape and it is functional, what would be the size in
order to be חייב? chayav? Now it's not only a question in
order to be חייב, chayav, it's also a question we're going to
see in a minute that the rabbis let you actually use stones
in the bathroom even though they would normally be considered מוקצה. muktzah.
It's a general principle that because of כבוד הבריות, kevod habriyos, because
of human dignity, it could even override sometimes even in some narrow
cases some biblical issues, but certainly rabbinic restrictions, issues when things relate
to to human dignity. So they let you so even though the
stones were מוקצה muktzah they let you use them in the bathroom
but only stones that were considered to be like appropriate for that
use.
So why can't you grab a
hammer to get used in the bathroom? Well you can't, הוצאה, hotzaah,
we're talking about מוקצה muktzah right now. Okay so anyway, okay, so
how big would they have to be? What would be their size
that would be appropriate to use? אמר לו, Amar lo, כזית כאגוז
וכביצה. kezayis ke-egoz u-che-beitzah.
So they gave him three amounts. He said כזית, kezayis, an olive,
an אגוז, egoz, a nut, and a ביצה, beitzah, an egg. So
apparently רש"י Rashi says that you would use different sizes at different
stages. I'm not exactly sure what רש"י Rashi I didn't get the
exact details of רש"י Rashi and anyway not worth sharing it. But
moving on, okay, so anyway, so they said what? PMI?
Yeah
right exactly, three different stages. Okay anyway אמר להו, amar lehu, he
said to them, וכי תורתני יכניס? ve-chi tortani yakhnis? So what should
you do? Should you take a little scale with you when you
go to the bathroom to weigh out exactly these three different sizes?
Says I need a little bit of a more functional definition than
that. Okay מנו וגמרו, minu ve-gamru, so they thought that was a
good point. So they took a vote and they decided מלא היד.
melo hayad. Okay as many stones as can fit into one hand.
So it's interesting because maybe if it's the different size, if it's
the size of the individual stone that makes it usable, maybe a
lot of little stones and one huge stone it's not all the
same what can fit into one hand. But anyway that's what they
said. Which by the way makes sense much more if we're talking
here about allowing you to use rather than the amount that you're
חייב chayav for carrying on שבת. Shabbos. Because then the fact that
he says what you want to bring scales and this and that
doesn't mean wouldn't logically mean that we should redefine what's considered sort
of significant for the biblical מלאכה melacha of carrying. But assuming we're
dealing with
rabbinic...
So why not? I mean for everything else we have these these
measurements you know they never asked us. Right. And and also the
idea that look if it's the use of something it's like olives
and
there's that article yeah olives is olives right? So tell people a
stone is what you use in the bathroom. I mean you have
to vote on exactly you know what.
Right well the second point well I would say the first point
is what I was alluding to but I went through it too
I went by it too quickly which is the fact that right
meaning everything else has sizes and what type of a of a
criticism is that so what you want to do take out a
scale yeah everything has sizes you measure whatever. And also נמנו וגמרו
nimnu ve'gamru normally we assume that you know the idea of שיעורים
shiurim is more like you know somewhat very often you assume הלכה
למשה מסיני halacha l'Moshe mi'Sinai although in this whole discussion by הוצאה
hotza'ah by שבת Shabbos it does seem more that they would look
case by case and assess you know it wasn't like that they
came down with all of these things הלכה halacha so there's still
a sense of deciding but still נמנו וגמרו nimnu ve'gamru is sort
of like yeah that's going to be inconvenient let's come up with
a better convenient type of a measure right? It does not sound
like we're deciding about the שיעור shiur for הוצאה hotza'ah and for
the חיוב chiyuv for carrying. So that's why I said it's makes
more sense if this question is what are you the Rabbis going
to let me use in the bathroom not sort of what is
the minimum amount for carrying. So then I could complain that that's
not a very functional usable standard you gave me give me a
better give me a better standard. So if it's within a rabbinic
context of what can I use and what gets around the you
know the מוקצה muktzah issues it makes this exchange makes a lot
more sense. So yeah I mean that's why I think you're right
and that's why I think it makes a lot more and רש''י
Rashi gives both possibilities of what the question being asked but because
of the נמנו וגמרו nimnu ve'gamru I agree it makes much more
sense that it's talking about the rabbinic issue of מוקצה. muktzah. Okay
so let's see where the גמרא Gemara goes. תניא Tanya רבי יוסי
אומר Rabbi Yose omer כגוז k'egoz כביצה. k'beitzah. So he says that
he says no it does go by these various sizes that's what
we allowed. And רבי שמעון בר רבי יוסי אומר Rabbi Shimon ben
Rabbi Yose omer now Rabbi Shimon his son says משום אביו mishum
aviv in his name of his father so it's a different version
of what his father said מלא היד melo hayad what fills it
fills a hand so maybe again it's the idea that once they
said one thing and then they reversed themselves.
Okay so again not clear if this is about carrying about using
but as we just discussed because this whole idea of that you
know that he said it needs to be a more functional definition
and they came out with a more functional one it seems like
the question of what do we allow you to use and to
address the מוקצה muktzah issue.
If we're making this a little bit more modern
what about like toilet paper? All right so we'll talk about this.
תנו רבנן Tanu rabbanan let's see we have more to say about
this. ג' אבנים מקורזלות מותר להכניס לבית הכסא. Gimel avanim mekurzalot mutar
l'hachnis l'veit hakisei. So three stones which are מקורזלות mekurzalot which are
like you know sort of shaped you know a little bit pointed
not too pointed I hope but whatever a little bit anyway but
they're the right shape to be using. They have an right they're
a little you know narrow. Anyway you can bring them into the
bathroom. So again this is clear that now we are talking not
about the minimum amount for carrying but what you're allowed to do
again this is not about this is not about carrying in a
כרמלית karmelit it's not about anything it's about specifically about a
מוקצה muktzah issue. וכמה שיעורן vekamah shiuran and what is their
size? רבי מאיר אומר כגוז. Rabbi Meir omer k'egoz. רבי יהודה אומר
כביצה. Rabbi Yehuda omer k'beitzah. So before we had all three being
said at once now we see that it's actually a it's actually
a debate of תנאים Tannaim what their minimum size is. אמר רבין
בר פפא אמר רב חסדא Amar Ravin bar Papa amar Rav Chisda
כמחלוקת כאן כך מחלוקת באתרוג. kemachloket kan kach machloket b'esrog. The same
way there's a debate of whether something is a size of a
nut or an egg there's also a debate by an אתרוג esrog
what is the minimum size of an אתרוג. esrog. So
the גמרא Gemara says כמחלוקת כך מחלוקת אתרוג. kemachloket kach machloket esrog.
התם מתניתין הכא ברייתא. Hatam matnitin hacha baraita. What are you doing
comparing a ברייתא baraita to a משנה? mishna? The אתרוג esrog debate
is a משנה mishna the minimum size by an אתרוג. esrog. Here
it's a ברייתא. baraita. So you know people know the משנה mishna
better than the ברייתא. baraita. אלא ella so here's how you should
say it. כמחלוקת באתרוג kemachloket b'esrog the same way there's a known
debate of an אתרוג esrog whether it's the size of a nut
or an egg כך מחלוקת כאן kach machloket kan there is also
a debate here whether that what the size is for the stones
for the bathroom. Isn't it fascinating you know it's in general take
a step back like how much time the גמרא Gemara spends on
certain topics rather than others. Like the גמרא Gemara basically you know
I mean you realize how much we've done already just about carrying
right? I think I counted the דפים dappim there's something like 40
45 דפים dappim related to carrying in this entire מסכת masechet which
is about 140 דף dap so a third of the מסכת masechet
is devoted to carrying and then we have another whole מסכת עירובין
masechet Eiruvin which is devoted to carrying out of the 39 מלאכות
melachos of שבת Shabbos and מוקצה muktzah and everything else. So anyways
if you also think about dealing with bathroom and the stones and
all that type of stuff like we had a lot of that
in ברכות Berachos you know more than would seem sort of normal
that we would expect it. Anyway we're back to that topic so
it's quite interesting which are the areas that you know sort of
get more focus than others. Anyway so the גמרא Gemara says like
this you know maybe we have the luxury of not worrying about
this we have running water we have toilet paper you know for
them obviously it was a major thing but anyway let's take a
look. What?
Their digestion also comes up.
Yeah, that's interesting. It's right. Their digestion and those issues. Yeah, it's
true. All right, so the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay. אמר רב Amar Rav אמר רב יהודה Amar Rav Yehuda אבל
לא את הפייס. aval lo et hapayas.
So this doesn't apply to פייס. payas. So what that basically is,
is like a clump of earth. If you try to use like
a hardened clump of earth to wipe yourself, that you're not allowed
to, because of obvious reasons. It might feel hard now, but you
start trying to use it and it'll crumble in your hands. So
מאי פייס? mai payas? אמר רב זירא Amar Rav Zeira כרשיני בבליתא.
karshinei bavlita. The, you know, it was basically like, it would be
called pebbles. Thank you. Babylonian pebbles, Babylonian like, you know, dirt. So
רש״י Rashi says, why Babylonian? So רש״י Rashi says because in בבל
Bavel it was a very like moist land and you would have
these like clumps of dirt. So basically Babylonian clumps. All right, so
that, no, because that would like crumble in your hand. אמר רבא
Amar Rava אסור למשמש בצרור בשבת. asur lemashmesh betzror beShabbat.
Now we're going to talk about using them. So you cannot, you
cannot use, you know, למשמש lemashmesh means basically, you know, used to
wipe yourself with a rock on בשבת beShabbat כדרך שמשמש בחול kederech
shemeshmesh bechol the same way you can do it in the weekday.
So it sounds like you can't use it at all. Yes, you
can use it in a weekday, not on בשבת. beShabbat. So מתקיף
לה מר זוטרא Matkif lah Mar Zutra ליסתכן? listaken? So you should
endanger yourself? If you're not doing this, you know, presumably it wasn't
understood that it was just
about becoming dirty, but it was actually, you know, if you were
having a hard time actually defecating, so by stimulating yourself, you
know, in that area,
it would help you relieve yourself. So if you're not going to
use a rock, what?
With a stone?
With a stone. Yeah. A sharp stone?
No, not too sharp. I don't know. Well,
you know, this happens sometimes based on the amount of time you
sit
on the toilet or whatever, and you know, whatever, it can sometimes
help you actually relieve yourself. So it said you can't use a
stone to help you do this.
Isn't that for wiping yourself at all?
Yeah, not just wiping. It's wiping but it's also doing it in
a way that helps you actually relieve yourself by stimulating that area.
Okay, so, right. So therefore he says, so what are you supposed
to do? You're supposed to endanger yourself? I mean, if you need
to go and you're not able to? So it says, no, כלאחר
יד. kelachar yad. Well, כדרך kederech can be read in two ways.
It says
you can't use it on בשבת beShabbat just like... meaning, does it
mean you can't use it? Yes, you can use it in the
weekday, but you can't use it on בשבת? beShabbat? Or you can't
use it in the same way you do it on the weekday?
So that's how it explains it. No, כלאחר יד kelachar yad you're
allowed to do it, but you have to do it in a
slightly unusual way. אמר רב ינאי Amar Rav Yannai it doesn't give
you details about how to make it כלאחר יד. kelachar yad. Yes,
it's a good question. We'll take a minute and see in the
גמרא Gemara what type of problems can come out. Okay.
So let's take a look.
So, right, so we'll see in a minute what are the problems
the גמרא Gemara is concerned with why it would have to be
כלאחר יד. kelachar yad. Alright. אמר רב ינאי Amar Rav Yannai אם
יש מקום קבוע לבית הכסא im yesh makom kavua leveit hakisei מלא
היד. melo hayad. Now we allowed you to go ahead and to
take a handful of rocks with you to the bathroom. That's if
there's a fixed place for the bathroom. Then you could take a
whole handful because then if you don't wind up using all of
them, they'll be there for the next person to use. ואם לאו
veim lav but if not, כהכרע מדוכה קטנה של בשמים. kehechrei meducha
ketana shel besamim. So, or כהכרע kehechra there's exactly a question where
to put the comma here, but anyway, כהכרע. kehechra. So what does
כהכרע kehechra mean? So רש״י Rashi says it means like the average
amount. We gave three amounts before: we gave an olive, what did
we say? A nut, an olive, a nut, and ביצה. beita. So
הכרע hachra the middle amount, is the size of the nut. תוספות
Tosafot reads it כהכרע מדוכה קטנה של בשמים kehechrei meducha ketana shel
besamim which means like one of these small legs that's used in
a, like in a, in a mortar for spices. So that's a
different size. All right. But anyway, so בקיצור bekitzur if it's not
a fixed בית הכסא beit hakisei if it's a fixed you can
take a lot because even if you have leftover a handful, somebody
else to use it. But if it's not a fixed and you're
the only one going there, we only let you take a smaller
amount.
Is that because of the amount you need or is it because
of somebody else?
Meaning, like is this amount... but again, it is a מוקצה muktzeh
issue, and we're doing it for כבוד הבריות kevod habriyot so you
know, there's a whole balance of concerns. On the one hand, we
care about your כבוד הבריות kevod habriyot on the other hand, we
don't want to give you a blanket היתר hetter to do as
much מוקצה muktzeh as you want. So we take in various factors.
So yes, you might... if you're clearly not going to need that
amount, you don't. But you don't know how much you'll need. So
if we know that it's possible that other people could use it,
then we'll let you take... then we'll be a little bit more
generous in what we assume might be the amount you'll use because
even if you don't wind up using it, somebody else will. So
that's at least the way רש״י Rashi explains the difference if it's
a fixed בית הכסא. beit hakisei. So now the גמרא Gemara says...
so anyway, it's an important question about where to put the comma
here, because רש״י Rashi reads that כהכרע kehechra period, and then you
read מדוכה קטנה של בשמים. meducha ketana shel besamim. If you want
to use a small like a, you know, pestle that's used in
the grinding of spices, now what are you doing using that for
your, you know, for your, for your bathroom purposes? it's all going
on the previous statement, we're not even talking about it anymore, but
at least according to רש"י Rashi we're actually talking about using this
actual object that's used for grinding spices and all of a sudden
now you've decided you want to use it for your toilet paper.
So אמר רב ששת, Amar Rav Sheshet, so said רב ששת Rav
Sheshet either talking about this pestle used in the grinding of spices
or just talking in general, אם יש לה עד מותר. Im yesh
lah ed mutar. If you have a stone that is let's say
normally not a stone that you would use,
it is take a look at תוספות, Tosafot, right? תוספות Tosafot אמר
רב ששת אם יש לה עד. Amar Rav Sheshet im yesh lah
ed. תוספות Tosafot does
not say this is talking about the spices anymore. מוכח באפי נפשיה
הוא. Muchach b'apei nafshih hu. פירוש: Peirush: מותר לקנח באפילו גדולה יותר
מכביצה אם יש לה עד. Mutar l'kaneach b'afilo gedola yoteira m'kabbeita im
yesh lah ed. או אם יש לה הרבה ממלוא יד Oh im
yesh lah harbe mimal yad מותר ליטול כולן. mutar litol kulan. דכיון
דיש לה עד הוכנו כולן. Dekivun deyesh lah ed huchnu kulan.
So עד ed basically means if there is a mark, if there's
a stain, if it's been previously used a rock, then you can
use it even if it is bigger than the smaller amount or
even if you're taking more than is the handful because the idea
of limiting you to a certain size or a handful is a
מוקצה muktzah issue. But if it's already been used, then it's no
longer מוקצה muktzah because then of course it's set aside, it's pre-designated
toilet paper, so you no longer have the limit.
Okay, so previously used is now actually okay. Now again, I just
point this out because I was maybe doing it too quickly a
minute ago, but רש"י Rashi says we're talking about actually using a
pestle for grinding spices that has on it the stain that has
been used in the bathroom. So
thankfully anyway that's like a completely bizarre scenario. So תוספות Tosafot reads,
תוספות Tosafot reads the spices thing referring to the previous line, right?
Big question here where you put the period. Anyway, the previous discussion
and now we're on a totally new topic. If it actually was
previously used and has a stain then it's not a מוקצה muktzah
issue anymore, then it's designated and then you can go ahead and
use as much as you want. So the גמרא Gemara says מיתבי,
Meitvei, I'll ask you on this: עשרה דברים מביאין את האדם לידי
תחתוניות. Asara devarim meivi'in et ha'adam lidei tachtoniyot. Ten things bring a
person to hemorrhoids. ואלו הן V'elu hen and these are they: האוכל
עלי קנים ועלי גפנים Ha'ochel alei kanim v'alei gefanim if you eat
the leaves of reeds and the leaves of grapevines, grape
leaves I guess,
what, yeah, ולולבי גפנים v'lulavei gefanim or the I guess the I
don't know the vines of the grapes, ומורגי בהמה בלא מלח umorigi
behema belo melach
and the sort of marbled flesh of an animal
like you know the stuff that looks very or רש"י Rashi says
it means like rough, like things like the tongue or the inner
cheek, the type of the skin that's very that's very that's rough.
That type of the flesh of the animal without or it has
not been salted. ושדרה של דג Vishidra shel dag or the spine
of a fish. ודג מליח שלא בשלו כל צרכו Vedag maliach shelo
bisho kol tzorko a salted fish that has not been fully cooked.
והשותה שמרי יין Vehashoteh shimrei yayin if you drink the lees of
wine. והמקנח בסיד ובחרסית Vehamokaneach besid ubecharsif if you wipe yourself
when you're going to the bathroom with plaster or with or with
pottery. ובצרור ובצרור Betzror ubetzror some say this is a continuation of
the same or separately, ובצרור ubetzror or בצרור bitzror שקנח בו חבירו
shekineach bo chaveiro with a rock that your friend has used. So
a previously used rock. ויש אומרים אף התולה את עצמו בבית הכסא
Ve'yesh omrim af hatoleh et atzmo beveit hakisei and others say even
if you suspend yourself in the bathroom, meaning that you sort of
sit you know you go sitting down without sitting on something, if
you squat basically. Anyway, so you see what? Yes.
Why are the rabbis doing? Well the גמרא Gemara is a medical
text?
Well, but they're concerned about, this is
totally, this particular, is it a ברייתא? braita?
I don't know, it's
purely medical, it's nothing הלכה. halakha.
Correct,
but that you have, that's not at all uncommon in the גמרא.
Gemara. I mean I don't think the גמרא Gemara it's
like thrown in someone will make a mistake this is medicine not
medical.
Right,
but you have that, I mean you have a whole like, I
mean it's not unusual. I mean look you have, I mean you
know the גמרא Gemara has אגדתא, aggadata, the גמרא, Gemara, I understood,
but they but they felt that they had
a leadership position amongst the Jewish people and that this was the
knowledge that they felt was the best knowledge and it was their
responsibility to let people know about this, you know? So I don't
understand if your rabbi gets up in the middle of the שול
shul and says I want to remind everyone that you should check
the batteries of your smoke detectors
because because there've been cases where people didn't check the batteries and
there've been terrible tragedies, would you say that's not your job, that's
not הלכה? halakha? You know, people are in certain positions, they have
a responsibility to their community. Now you might not necessarily,
okay, that's true because it's not because the primary discourse is that
of הלכה, halakha, but in the context of discussion. But in the
context of discussing it, we discuss אגדתא aggadata and we discuss medical
issues and we discuss a wide range of things.
But you're emphasizing the role of doctor.
No, I don't think that's fair. They are not speaking about this
with like the voice of I mean הלכה halachic authority. They are
informing you. They're informing you. They're informing you. They are not no.
There are some גמרות gemaras where actually medical issues factor into actual
הלכה halachic rulings, but here they're just informing you of things that
you need to be careful about. I don't see this as גזירת
הכתוב gezeirat hakatuv or anything. I think it is a very responsible
public service announcement.
Right.
They're just talking and they're saying,
you know, oh, by the way... it's not a by the way.
All right, let's continue. It's organized. I know, but they're not they're
saying it as advice. Okay, let's go on. The גמרא gemara says
like this. לא קשיא. lo kashya. Anyway, so how can you say
you can use something that's been used before?
Look, it's unhealthy.
So the גמרא gemara says לא קשיא הא בלחא הא ביבשתא. lo
kashya ha belacha ha beyaveshta. Yeah, it's different whether it's still moist
or dry.
If it's already dry, then it's not a problem. ואי בעית אימא,
ve'ee ba'it eima, if you want you could say כאן מצד אחד
כאן משני צדדים. kan mitzad echad kan mishenei tzedadim. You'll use the
other side of the rock. ואי בעית אימא הא דידיה הא דחבריה,
ve'ee ba'it eima ha deideh ha dechavreh, it matters if it's somebody
else's or it's your own. Okay, so anyway now we have found
out that we don't have a מוקצה muktzah problem if it's been
previously used and can be used again because then it is designated.
But all the discussions about filling in your hand and or the
minimum sizes or whatever are when it really is מוקצה. muktzah. אמר
אביי לרב יוסף, amar Abaye l'Rav Yosef, ירדו עליהן גשמים וניטשטשו מהו?
yardu aleihen geshamim venistashteshu mahu?
Let's say rain fell on them and then it sort of and
it somewhat washed away the mark. Can are they still are they
still okay to be used? Maybe, you know, maybe they become מוקצה
muktzah again. אמר ליה, amar lei, אם היה רישומו ניכר מותר. im
hayah rishumo nikar mutar. No, if you can still see some mark
on it then it's okay, then it's still considered designated and not
מוקצה. muktzah. בעי מיניה רבה בר רב שילא מרב חסדא. ba'ei minei
Rabbah bar Rav Shila miRav Chisda.
Like I said, this goes into those other גמרות gemaras in ברכות
Berachot that are so focused on the bathroom. מהו להעלותן אחריו לגג?
mahu l'haalotan acharayv lagag?
Can you take them with you to the rooftop? Now what's the
issue? רש"י Rashi says the issue is טרחא, tircha, that not only
is it a מוקצה muktzah problem but you're schlepping them up to
the rooftop. But that doesn't so much fit with the later גמרא.
gemara. תוספות Tosafot says that the issue here really is that maybe
they would often use the rooftop as a place for their bathroom
and the question here is look, we're allowing you to move מוקצה,
muktzah, but that's because maybe when there's no alternative. But maybe if
it's the rooftop, maybe you should have put stones up there from
before שבת Shabbat and designated them and we're not going to allow
you to, you know, to do מוקצה muktzah if you had an
alternative. So אמר ליה גדול כבוד הבריות שדוחה לא תעשה שבתורה. amar
lei gadol kevod habriyot shedochi lo ta'aseh shebaTorah. And this is the
principle that's operative here that allows us to say that we can
sort of waive within certain parameters, not absolutely, but waive the concerns
of מוקצה. muktzah. There's a כבוד הבריות kevod habriyot issue, there's a
human dignity issue and therefore even if maybe you could have a
little bit taken some precautions, right now you need these stones and
you don't have what to wipe yourself with, so you can go
ahead and take them to the rooftop. Now the לא תעשה, lo
ta'aseh, it overrides a לא תעשה. lo ta'aseh. There's a גמרא gemara
in ברכות, Berachot, so the גמרא gemara says don't treat that too
literally. The primary לא תעשה lo ta'aseh it means is rabbinic, that
since you're supposed to listen to all the rabbinic legislation because of
לא תסור, lo tassur, not to swerve from what the rabbis say
ימין ושמאל, yamin usmol, which is linked to a biblical verse, so
it refers to that לא תעשה lo ta'aseh of listening to the
rabbis or the גמרא gemara has maybe one or two other cases
like passively or things relating to issues דברים שבממון, devarim shebamamon, but
fundamentally this is used relating to rabbinic restrictions that כבוד הבריות kevod
habriyot can override and it's actually interesting to look at the halachic
literature when sometimes the issue of כבוד הבריות kevod habriyot comes up.
You know, or another issue that sometimes comes up interestingly is like
the idea of like שלום בית. shalom bayit. When things like שלום
בית shalom bayit or כבוד הבריות kevod habriyot comes up to allow
you to say yeah, there actually is a restriction here but it's
rabbinic and this is a greater value and that actually can override
in certain circumstances. Now it's one thing to say like in certain
circumstances like that,
you know, that are
like accidental it confronts as opposed to like a complete, you know,
rewriting of the law for that. No, fundamentally obviously we're not saying
there's no מוקצה, muktzah, there is מוקצה muktzah but when it abuts
כבוד הבריות, kevod habriyot, then we're going to allow כבוד הבריות kevod
habriyot to override and this is exactly what the גמרא gemara is
struggling with about, yeah, but let's say you could have prevented it.
So for example, well let's read another line in the גמרא gemara
and then I'll talk about practical application. So the גמרא gemara says
like this. יתיב מריימר וקאמר להאי שמעתא, yativ Mareimar veka'amar l'hai shema'ata,
מריימר Mareimar was sitting and telling over this discussion. איתיביה רבינא למריימר,
eitiveih Ravina l'Mareimar, so רבינא Ravina asked מריימר. Mareimar. רבי אליעזר אומר
נוטל אדם קיסם משלפניו לחצות בו שיניו. Rabbi Eliezer omer notel adam
kisam meshelifanav lachatzot bo shinav. So Rabbi Eliezer says a person can
take a twig like from the, you know, from things that are
in front of him, like from sticks on the ground, in order
to use to pick it off or was it no no no
just pick it off of the ground. It's a מוקצה muktzah issue,
pick it off of the ground in order to use it to
pick his teeth so that he doesn't have little pieces of food
sticking out of his teeth which also looks unseemly. וחכמים אומרים לא
ייטול אלא מן האבוס של בהמה. vachachamim omrim lo yitol ela min
ha'evus shel behema. No,
you can only take it if you're taking it out of the
trough of the animal. the animal meaning if it's if it's animal
food and therefore it's not מוקצה muktzeh set aside for animals so
it's not מוקצה muktzeh but taking it off the ground you cannot
so you see there we did not allow you to use the
מוקצה muktzeh thing to pick your teeth at least according to the
חכמים chachamim as opposed to רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer so even though
so you see we don't allow it so the גמרא Gemara says
הכי השתא hachi hashta how can you make that comparison התם אדם
קובע מקום לסעודתו hatam adam kove'a makom l'se'udato הכא אדם קובע מקום
לבית הכסא hacha adam kove'a makom l'veit hakisei there a person has
a place where you're going to have your meal so there actually
yeah you know you'll have your meal there and you should have
some things some toothpicks designated for you to use during your meal
here maybe yeah it would often you'd go to the bathroom on
the roof but you know you don't know where you're going to
be when you need to go to the bathroom so therefore if
you you know we do not we we even if you know
you could have a little said you should have put them up
on the roof but you never know where you're going to need
these stones and therefore we allow you to use them whenever you
need them because it's a כבוד הבריות kevod ha-beriyot issue. So that
raises interesting questions about how much are we going to say well
you should have taken care of this beforehand and
you know it does come up with whole issue about cutting toilet
paper because so I'm not going to discuss now whether you know
the איסור issur of cutting toilet paper is it like making a
vessel you know if it's if it's totally disposable and how much
do you really care about the exact size and this and that
let's work with the assumption that we tend to work with which
is that you're not allowed to cut toilet paper on שבת. Shabbat.
So then the question becomes so what do you do you find
yourself in a bathroom where it doesn't have the tissues it doesn't
have cut toilet paper so what do you do?
So so I heard somebody who said to me says well just
use it without cutting it and then you flush the toilet and
then like the water of the toilet like separates it which
okay that was interesting anyway it does work yes but then it's
not so כבוד הבריות kevod ha-beriyot to the guy coming after you.
Anyway so this would be a case where look according to you
know many I would say I would say highly majority of opinions
would say that even to cut it on the perforations because it's
all disposable and whatnot is you know is is a דרבנן d'rabbanan
and even if you want to be concerned that it might be
worse than that so you know you do it like a little
bit of a שינוי shinui or you do it כלאחר יד k'le-achar
yad you know you do it with the back of your hand
you know you use your teeth or something whatever anyway so and
once it's דרבנן d'rabbanan it's כבוד הבריות kevod ha-beriyot you know obviously
and therefore in and therefore that's what would be fine but if
you too much you know apply this גמרא Gemara you could say
well that's if you're maybe your friend's bathroom or this or that
but if it's your own bathroom and you should have known better
you know maybe we wouldn't say that but in general we don't
say you know that we'd say that if you really find yourself
in that situation and it's a כבוד הבריות kevod ha-beriyot issue so
you know you make you know you get it down to a
דרבנן d'rabbanan level and you're fine yes.
How could you argue that it's not דרבנן d'rabbanan because someone else
with with perforations someone else already started the cutting?
Yeah but it doesn't matter I mean actually you know מכה בפטיש
makeh b'patish is when it's gotten up to its exact and it
hasn't gotten to like its final state or something but anyway you
know look it's we're not going to fully analyze that it probably
you know most probably is definitely דרבנן d'rabbanan even if you cut
it on the perforations but even if you want to be concerned
that it's not you know you do it somehow with like the
back of your hand or some type of a way use two
fingers to pull it off rather than you know the normal way
and you do it in that and then you're and then you're
fine. I actually had somebody once told me this is not exactly
the same but it's similar so he was on a boat and
and I don't know what happened now on the cruise ship and
he went to the bathroom on שבת Shabbat you know and they
and you know he closed the door and the light went on.
So now what did he do right how does he get out
of the bathroom? So going to be there the whole שבת? Shabbat?
So he says said you had to be on the boat to
realize the answer. He said what he did was he just unlatched
the lock and by the and the movement of the boat the
door just opened by itself. So yes so great question what is
so is it better to cut the toilet paper than for the
tissues if you need to open it and you have like that
you know?
I'm not going to deal with that right
now there's too many to talk about like leaves or something like
that you know I would imagine that leaves would work.
Oh so that's a good question and we're going to get to
that at the bottom because there is another גמרא Gemara which the
גמרא Gemara will allude to part of that discussion things that are
flammable and that you would use for toilet paper were considered to
make you susceptible to witchcraft and therefore they did not use flammable
objects.
So toilet
paper is flammable.
Yes good thing we don't have any witchcraft around anymore.
Okay so anyway flammable just about five years
ago there were lots of it.
There you go. All right so now the גמרא Gemara continues
okay.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this הכי השתא hachi hashta oh
we did that אמר רב הונא amar Rav Huna אסור לפנות באסטניא
בשבת asur lifanot b'istanya b'Shabbat you cannot go to the bathroom defecate
in a plowed over field on שבת. Shabbat. אסטניא istanya was a
field that was plowed that was not planted. Well no but it
wasn't planted so there's no seed so right it doesn't seem like
it would be an issue about זורע. zore'a. So let's take a
look. מאי טעמא mai ta'ama what's the reasoning? אילימא משום דאבשא ilima
mishum davsha
because of trampling you're trampling on the field and therefore you're you
know basically just causing a monetary loss to your friend you don't
want to walk on this guy's nice you know plowed over field.
So אפילו בחול נמי afilu b'chol nami even during the weekday. דאלא
משום אבנא de-ela mishum avna so rather it would be because of
rocks. So what does it mean rocks?
So what? I'm sorry, I meant grass. I said rocks, but I
meant grass. Thank you. So rather it's because of grass, which means
that the way רש״י Rashi explains it is that because specifically maybe
in this plowed field that hasn't been planted, there's a lot of
grass growing and therefore if you take a rock to wipe yourself,
you'll inadvertently pull up grass. So if that's the reason, ואמר ריש
לקיש Ve'amar Reish Lakish צרור שעלו בו עשבים tzror she'alu bo asavim
מותר לקנח בו. mutar lekanne'ach bo. If there's grass growing on a
rock, you can pick it up and wipe yourself. והתולש ממנו בשבת
חייב חטאת, Vehatolesh mimenu beShabbos chayav chatas, but if you pour from
it... pour from it...
if you tear the grass away intentionally, you are חייב שבת. chayav
Shabbos. So what is the reason? Because and now we get to
part of the question related before about the שינוי shinuy issue. One
type of a concern beyond מוקצה muktzah is that you are tearing
grass. So we have grass growing off of a rock, which is
interesting. It's growing on the rock, maybe it's moss, right? It's not
really growing off of the ground. Is that really considered growing from
the ground? Is that really considered to be תולש tolesh on שבת
Shabbos if you're tearing it off of a rock? So we'll look
about that in more in a minute, but here the גמרא Gemara
is saying that if you're using the rock and maybe inadvertently grass
will tear off, but you're not intending for it, so therefore it's
not a problem, even though if you intentionally tear it off, it
is going to be חייב. chayav. So you see it's not a
problem. אלא דילמא נקיט מעילויה ושדי לתתאי. Ela dilma nakit me'iluya veshadei
letatta'i.
Here's the problem. The problem is that maybe you'll take some stuff
from above and you'll put it below, meaning you'll take some rock
or whatever to wipe yourself with and then you'll put it into
a hole when you're done with it ומחייב משום דרבה. umechayev mishum
deRabbah. דאמר רבה De'amar Rabbah האי סולא גומא וטמימה. hai sola guma
u'temimah.
If you had a hole and you filled it, בבית חייב משום
בונה, bevayis chayav mishum boneh, in the house you're חייב chayav because
of building, בשדה חייב משום
חורש, besadeh chayav mishum choresh, in the field you're חייב chayav for
חורש choresh because you're making the ground fit to be planted. So
since this ground here, it's not like you're out in the forest,
it's a type of a ground that is about that could be
used soon to be planted, if the way you rearrange the landscape
by taking some dirt and putting it back down levels it, then
inadvertently you will come to be חייב chayav for doing חורש. choresh.
And that's a little bit different than the אינו מתכוין eino miskaven
by the grass. אינו מתכוין Eino miskaven by the grass, it wasn't
necessarily going to happen, it was completely inadvertent. Here you actually are
consciously filling this hole up. You might not be aware that that's
a חיוב חטאת, chiyuv chatas, but you'll come to fill up a
hole by taking something and putting something down and therefore that's the
problem. So now we're going to look at the issue about the
grass and inadvertent, and that's one of the concerns that we have
here. So ואמר ריש לקיש Ve'amar Reish Lakish in addition to מוקצה,
muktzah, צרור שעלו בו עשבים tzror she'alu bo asavim מותר לקנח בו.
mutar lekanne'ach bo.
If you have a rock that has grass on it, you can
use it to wipe yourself. והתולש ממנו בשבת חייב חטאת, Vehatolesh mimenu
beShabbos chayav chatas,
and if you tear grass from it on שבת, Shabbos, you're חייב.
chayav. אמר רב פפא Amar Rav Pappa שמע מינה מדרייש לקיש shema
mina mideReish Lakish האי פרפיסא שרי לטלטולי. hai parfisa sharei letiltulei. This
פרפיסא, parfisa,
which is some type of a leaf that has dirt and plants
in it that's on the ground, you can lift it off. Because
the question here is the following: is that why, forget tearing the
grass off of the rocks, why when you lift the rock up
that has the grass on it is that not תולש? tolesh? Because
now you're separating the rock that has the grass on it from
the dirt below. So essentially you're separating the grass, right? When the
grass was on the rock and the rock was on the dirt,
it was all like one unit. You lift up the rock, you're
separating the grass from the dirt, why isn't that תולש? tolesh? But
we're saying here it's not, from the same way it's not, it's
also true about this פרפיסא. parfisa. Now what is this פרפיסא? parfisa?
So one explanation רש״י Rashi says is that it's basically a plant...
like a flower pot that has a hole on the bottom, so
it's connected to the ground, it has a plant growing up, you
lift it from the ground, there's now air space between the bottom
and the dirt and the ground, and that's not considered to be
תולש. tolesh. But then he brings another fascinating explanation of the גאונים
Geonim of what this פרפיסא parfisa is. If you take a look
at רש״י, Rashi, he says the following. It's about twenty lines from
where the lines get wide. מצאתי Matzati is where the line starts.
He says ובתשובת גאונים מצאתי uvitshuvat geonim matzati שעושים תותלות she'osim tutalot
מכפות תמרים. mikapot tmarim.
You make sort of like, you know, containers out of, what do
you call it, palm leaves. וממלאין אותם עפר וזבל דהמן. umemalin otam
afar vezebel dehaman. You fill it with dirt or whatever and with,
you know, fertilizer. וכופיהו ט״ו יום לפני ראש השנה. vekofyehu tet-vav yom
lifnei Rosh Hashanah.
And like, you know, two to three weeks before ראש השנה. Rosh
Hashanah. עושים כל אחד ואחד לשם כל קטן וקטנה שבבית. osim kol
echad ve'echad leshem kol katan vektanah shebabayis.
You make a separate one for every child in the house. וזורעין
לתוכן פול המצרי או קטנית. vezore'in letochan pol hamitzri o kitnis.
And you plant in it various types of legumes which apparently will
sprout quickly. וקורין לו פורפיסא. vekorin lo purfisa. I have no idea
what that name means, but anyway, they call it פורפיסא. purfisa. וצומח
vetsomeach and then it would sprout before ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah. ובערב
ראש השנה uve'erev Rosh Hashanah נוטל כל אחד שלו. notel kol echad
shelo.
Every person takes the one designated for him or her. ומחזירו סביבות
ראשו umachziro sevivot rosho שבע פעמים. sheva pe'amim. And you turn it
seven times around your head, right? ואומר זה תחת זה זה חליפתי.
ve'omer ze tachat ze ze chalifati. חליפתי וזה תמורתי ומשליכו לנהר. chalifati
v'zeh t'murati umashlicho l'nahar.
So there you have a very early Geonic basis for this, right,
for this idea of כפרות, Kapporos, כפרות Kapporos and תשליך. Tashlich. Oh,
that's a good point, yeah. I never thought of that, connected to
the תשליך, Tashlich, תשליך Tashlich without mistreating any animals. Exactly. So how
did that change?
I have no idea, but anyway, it's quite fascinating, a little thing
in the middle of this whole discussion of wiping yourself. So anyway,
so there according to רש״י, Rashi, that's what this פרפיסא parpisa was.
So back to the
גמרא. Gemara. האי פרפיסא שרי לטלטלו. Hai parpisa shari l'taltulei. You can
carry it because it's not considered to be תולש toleish because it's
just because it's lifted from the ground. מתקיף לה רב כהנא: Matkif
lah Rav Kahana: אם אמרו לצורך, יאמרו שלא לצורך? im amru l'tzorech,
yomru shelo l'tzorech? Just because you're allowed to do it for a
need for the bathroom, you can't do it שלא לצורך. shelo l'tzorech.
Generally, there might be an איסור דרבנן issur d'rabanan to take something
and lift it off of the ground even if you're not physically
like pulling the roots out, but this type of thing was on
the ground and you lifted it off, that's a problem. We only
allowed it for the bathroom purposes; we wouldn't allow it for סתם
stam purposes. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says, אמר אביי: Amar
Abaye: פרפיסא, הא ואתא לידן, לימא בה מילתא. parpisa, ha va'ata l'yadan,
leima bah milta. This פרפיסא parpisa now that we're talking about it,
let's say something about it. היה מונח על גבי קרקע והניחו על
גבי יתידות, חייב משום תולש. Haya munach al gabi karka v'hinicho al
gabi yeteidot, chayav mishum toleish. If it was right there on the
earth and you picked it up and you now suspended it off
of pegs, presumably there's air space between it and the ground but
nothing physically separating, you're חייב chayav for תולש. toleish. היה מונח על
גבי יתידות והניחו על גבי קרקע, חייב משום נוטע. Haya munach al
gabi yeteidot v'hinicho al gabi karka, chayav mishum notei'a. If you reversed
it, it was on the pegs and now you put it on
the ground, חייב משום נוטע, chayav mishum notei'a, you're חייב chayav for
planting.
Now רש״י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot both say, what the heck? You're
חייב chayav for planting and for uprooting? So then how were we
allowed to pick up the stone with the rocks and to go
ahead and say that this whole thing was allowed? So רש״י Rashi
and תוספות Tosafot both say you have to interpret that the גמרא
Gemara means like מדרבנן. mi'd'rabanan. It doesn't literally mean it; it means
it's
rabbinic תולש, toleish, it's rabbinic נוטע. notei'a. But, you know, it's—that's quite
of a stretch, and it doesn't sound that way, and one does
wonder if maybe there's a big difference between the case of the
stone and the case of the—and the case of this פרפיסא. parpisa.
The case of the stone, you know, again, what grass grows on
stone? I assume it means moss, right? So moss, I don't know,
how is moss different than grass? Does moss really, I mean, is
it—it
doesn't have roots in the same way.
Right. So I really wonder if, like, if you could say there's
a fundamental difference between moss on a stone, which, and the stone
on the ground, which is not considered growing from the ground, as
opposed to something which is, like, you know, in dirt in a
flower pot or whatever and you, that is considered like an extension
of the ground and it is really getting the nutrients through the
roots from the ground. One wonders if you could have made a
real big distinction between the rock/moss case and this case. But, but
there is this opinion, you know, the גמרא Gemara does say—initially say
they're the same and then here makes a radical shift and says
you're חייב. chayav. So רש״י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot read it as
meaning it's rabbinically restricted. Okay, but that's an important question about whether
taking something that's on the ground and you didn't pull up the
root but you sort of remove the whole thing and there's this
air space between, is that like an act of תולש toleish or
not. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara continues.
Where are we?
Okay. אמר רבי יוחנן: Amar Rabbi Yochanan: אסור לקנח בחרס בשבת. Assur
l'kane'ach b'cheres b'Shabbat. You cannot use חרס cheres pottery on שבת. Shabbat.
מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama? אילימא משום סכנה? Ilima mishum sakana? If it's
because of danger, that maybe it's too sharp and it'll actually hurt
you, and רש״י Rashi says like it'll lead out—or like—you know, right,
it'll hurt you interior, so then אפילו
בחול נמי? afillu b'chol nami? You shouldn't use it on the weekday.
אלא משום כשפים? Ela mishum k'shafim? Because of concerns of witchcraft. Like
I said, you use certain things to wipe yourself, it makes you
susceptible to witchcraft. אפילו בחול נמי לא. Afillu b'chol nami lo. So
even in the weekday you shouldn't. אלא משום השרת נימין. Ela mishum
hasharat nimin. So and this, Michael, gets back to the question before
about why we said to use a שינוי. shinuy. There's a concern
that as you're—if it's very sharp, you'll scrape away some hairs on
your body that are in that area and that'll be a problem
of, you know, תולש toleish or whatever, or גוזז, gozez, whatever it
is.
Okay, so that's דבר שאינו מתכוין.
davar she'eino mitkavein. Okay, so that's the answer. So if that's true,
דבר שאינו מתכוין, davar she'eino mitkavein, you're not מתכוין. mitkavein. So why
should that be an issue? You're not intending. אמר ליה רב נתן
בר אושעיא: גברא רבה אמר מילתא, נימרו בה טעמא. Amar lei Rav
Natan bar Oshaya: Gavra raba amar milta, neimru bah ta'ama. Look, a
great person said something, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said you can't do
it, we have to find a way to explain what the יישוב
yishuv is. So what does he mean don't do it on שבת?
Shabbat? He means even on שבת. Shabbat. לא מיבעיא בחול. Lo mibaya
b'chol. It goes without saying don't do it on the weekday, דאסור,
d'assur, it's forbidden because
of—because, you know, it's—it's maybe like a danger or witchcraft, it has
these other concerns. אבל בשבת, הואיל ואיכא תורת כלי עליו, שפיר דמי.
Aval b'Shabbat, ho'il v'ika torat kli alav, shapir dami. But by שבת,
Shabbat, maybe I should say better to use a piece of pottery
that maybe is a type of a vessel because it was part
of a vessel or something and it has less of the מוקצה
muktza concern, so maybe you should use it and avoid the מוקצה
muktza issue, even though it's more problematic because it has a chance
of injuring you. קא משמע לן: לא. Ka mashma lan: lo. Which
by the way is a very important point, because, you know, a
lot of people would feel
that, ah— This thing you shouldn't be using on a weekday, and
you shouldn't be using on שבת, Shabbos, even though by using it
on שבת Shabbos you'd avoid the מוקצה muktzah concern, it's not something
that you should be using, it's not, it's somewhat dangerous, don't use
it even on שבת. Shabbos. Okay.
רבא, Rava, wow that's beautiful. Yeah, it is. That's true. Sadly that
is not the way some people say. רבא מתני לה משום אשרשינים.
Rava matni la mishum ayei sharsinim. So רבא Rava said no. רבי
יוחנן's Rabbi Jochanan's concern was you're going to pull out hairs. דקשיא
ליה, De-kashya lei, and he thought that the problem was that even
though it's אינו מתכוין eino miskavein it's a problem. But then, דקשיא
ליה דרבי יוחנן אדרבי יוחנן, de-kashya lei de-Rabbi Jochanan ad-Rabbi Jochanan, he
was bothered that רבי יוחנן Rabbi Jochanan contradicts himself. מי אמר רבי
יוחנן אסור לקנח בחרס בשבת? Mi amar Rabbi Jochanan asur lekane'ach be-cheres
be-Shabbos?
How could רבי יוחנן Rabbi Jochanan say you can't use pottery, presumably
because it pulls out hairs? אלמא דבר שאינו מתכוין אסור, Alma davar
she-eino miskavein asur, sounds like even things you're not intending are forbidden
on שבת. Shabbos. ואמר רבי יוחנן הלכה כסתם משנה, Ve-amar Rabbi Jochanan
halacha ke-stam mishna, and רבי יוחנן Rabbi Jochanan says we go by
a סתם משנה. stam mishna. דתנן, De-tnan, and we taught, נזיר חופף
ומפספס אבל לא סורק, Nazir chofef u-mefaspeis aval lo soreik, a נזיר
Nazir can basically like sort of like
run his hand through his hair and he can like brush his
hair, but he can't use like a fine comb because that will
pull out hairs. So the point is something that will definitely pull
out hairs is a problem, but other types of ways of combing
his hair that won't definitely pull it out is okay because it's
אינו מתכוין eino miskavein and it's not פסיק רישא, psik reisha, it
won't definitely happen. And that's a סתם משנה. stam mishna. So if
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Jochanan rules like a סתם משנה, stam mishna, he
rules that אינו מתכוין, eino miskavein, not intended, if it won't definitely
happen is okay. So why should he have a problem with the
pottery? אלא מחוורתא כרב נתן בר אושיא. Ella mechvarta ke-Rav Natan bar
Oshaya.
So, you're right, it's not because of the pulling out hairs. The
point was even on שבת, Shabbos, you want to be פרום frum
and use this because it's not מוקצה? muktzah? No, don't use it
even on שבת. Shabbos. Okay. Now we end our discussion with talking
about the witchcraft. מאי כשפים? Mai kshafim? What's the witchcraft issue? כי
הא דרב חסדא ורבה בר רב הונא, Ki hadei Rav Chisda ve-Rabbah
bar Rav Huna, like רב חסדא Rav Chisda and רבה בר רב
הונא, Rabbah bar Rav Huna, הוו קאזלי בארבא, havu ka-azlei be-arba, they
were going on a boat. אמר להו ההיא מטרוניתא, Amar le-hu ha-hi
matrunita, a certain matron, a certain woman, said to them, אוספן בהדייכו,
osfan bahadeichu, let me sit with you guys. ולא אוספוה, Ve-lo osfua,
they didn't want her to sit with them. אמרה איהי מילתא, Amra
eehi milta, so she apparently knew witchcraft, so she said some magic
words. אסרתה לארבא Asarta le-arba and the boat was bound, was not
able to continue moving. It was stuck. אמרי אינהו מילתא, Amri eehu
milta, so
they, it was like a battle
of the, they weren't saying witchcraft, it was called רש"י Rashi was
a שם טהרה, shem tahora, an acceptable name, I don't know, they
said some word. שריוה, Sharyua, and they allowed the boat to go.
אמרה להו, Amra le-hu, she said to them, מאי עביד לכו? mai
avid le-chu? What can I do to you? I want to get
back at you, but I can't, you're protected. Why are you protected?
דלא מקנחי לכו בחספא de-lo mekanaich le-chu be-chaspa because you don't use
when you go to the bathroom pottery, ולא קטלי לכו כינה ממאנייכו
ve-lo katlei le-chu kina me-manaiku
you don't kill louse on your garments, ולא שלחי לכו ירקא ואכלי
לכו מקישרא דאסר גינאי ve-lo shaleich le-chu yarka ve-achlei le-chu me-kishra de-asar
ginai and you don't pull out a vegetable and eat from the
bundle that the gardeners have, that the farmers have bundled. Like if
you have a bunch of whatever like carrots or something, you don't
pull a carrot out and eat it, you first undo the bundle
and then you eat it. Apparently if you pull out the vegetable
and eat it while everything is still in its bundle, that also
makes you susceptible to witchcraft. So these three things make you susceptible
to witchcraft: using pottery to wipe yourself, killing lice on your garments,
and pulling something out of a bundle of vegetables before undoing the
vegetables. They didn't do any of that, so she was stuck, she
couldn't attack them because they were protected.
All right, tomorrow to be continued.